Good morning,everyone.
早上好 同学们
This semester has started,officially today.
今天是本学期正式开学的第一天
Glad to see you here.
很高兴在这看到你们
Just a couple of announcement
我只想说几句话
and also hi to the extension school students.
还有向进修学院的同学们打声招呼
Last time we say hi to New Zealand.
上次我们向新西兰的同学问好
Today we are saying hi to Ireland.
今天轮到爱尔兰的同学了
In terms of sectioning
现在先说这里的本科生和研究生
for the undergrads and graduate students here,
分组问题
you'll get an email from Sean Achor tomorrow.
你们明天会收到Sean Achor的邮件
And you'll put in your section preference.
你们填好各自的想加入的小组
We are sectioning this weekend.
我们本周会分好小组
So it will be important that you submit your top preferences.
选择你最想加入的组非常重要
And next week we are starting.
下周我们就开始
Last time,if you remember the question that we ask,
还记得上节课的问题吗
the guiding question was "why positive psychology?"
最主要的问题是"为什么要学习积极心理学?"
And I mentioned three reasons,
我提到了三个原因
Why we need it as an independent field as opposed to just being
为何我们把它作为独立的研究 而不简单地
"well,let's do some studies on happiness,on relationships"
"研究一下幸福和爱情"
as it is always being done?
不像一贯人们所做的那样?
The reason why we need positive psychology is to shift
我们需要积极心理学是为了改变
the pendulum from the 21:1 ratio that we have today:
现在的21比1这个比率
for every one study on depression or anxiety,
每有一项关于抑郁或焦虑的研究
we have 21 studies on-- sorry,
就有21项 对不起
for one study on happiness or wellbeing,
应该是每有一项关于快乐或幸福的研究
we have 21 studies on depression and anxiety.
就有21项关于抑郁或焦虑的研究
We want to shift the pendulum slightly.
我们想稍微改变这个比率
And I mentioned three reason
我提过三个原因
why we want to shift this pendulum despite the fact
关于为什么要改变这个比率
that there are rising levels of depression around the world,
尽管世界上越来越多人抑郁
that anxiety has become epidemic globally―
而焦虑就像是全球性流行病
on college campuses in United States,China,Australia,UK.
遍布美国 中国 澳大利亚 英国所有大学
Despite that fact,I argue that we need to shift the pendulum
尽管如此 我还是认为我们该改变那比率
and do more "positive research",or in other words,
做更多"积极研究" 或者说
research that focuses on what works.
集中研究可行的事
And the reason is―
原因在于
the first reason that we gave and we are just finishing up is
我们之前讨论完的第一个原因是
because the question that we ask,
我们提出的问题很重要
whether it's the research questions that we ask,
无论它是不是我们的研究问题
or the questions that we ask of ourselves,
或我们为自己所问的
or our partners,matter.
或为我们的伴侣问的
And if our only questions,
如果我们只问同一类问题
or primarily our questions are "what is not working?
或只是问"有哪些不如意的事?
What is the problem?
出什么问题了?
Why are so many kids failing as a result of their circumstances?"
为什么那么多孩子因为成长环境而堕落?"
If we only ask these questions,
如果我们只问了这些问题
we will miss,literally miss an important part of reality,
就会错过现实中很重要的部分
just like you missed the children on the bus in the exercise.
像你们在练习中没看到公车上的孩子一样
Most of you did.
你们大多数人都没看到
And if we also ask the positive question,
如果我们也问积极问题
then some new possibilities,new quests open up,
那就会出现新的可能性 新的探索
just like they did for the researchers when they started to ask
就像他们对研究学者所问的一样
no longer "why do so many individuals fail?"
不再问"为什么有这么多人堕落?"
but started to ask "what do some individuals do and succeed?
而问"那些人是怎样取得成功的?
Why do some individuals succeed
为什么有些人能成功
despite the unfavorable circumstances?"
即使成长环境恶劣?"
And then we have the story of Marva Collins,
我们会以Marva Collins的故事为例
who exemplifies so many of themes
她的例子很典型 能说明很多观点
that we'll talk about throughout the course.
这些观点会贯穿我们整节课
What Marva Collins did
Marva Collins所做的
was help her students shift from the passive victim―
就是帮助她的学生从消极的受害者-
you are victims of your circumstances,
你是成长环境的受害者
of your upbringing,neighborhood,country,
是你的家庭教育 邻里关系 和社会环境的受害者
whatever it is―from a passive victim to an active agent.
诸如此类的 从消极的受害者变成积极的作用者
Yes,it's difficult. It's tough. It's unfair.
是的 那很困难 艰辛 不公平
However,it's your responsibility. No one is coming.
但这是你自己的责任 没人会来帮你
It's up to you to make that difference in your life.
能否改变自己的人生 由你自己决定
And she made a difference to thousands of people's lives
但她改变了千千万万人的人生
and continues to do so.
现在还在这么做
In other words,if we look at the case of Chicago school system
换句话说 如果我们看看芝加哥学院体制
where Marva Collins was teaching,the conventional,
Marva Collins就在那体制下执教
traditional question was-- if you remember―
还是那个老问题
"how can we keep these students in school
"怎样才能让学生们在学校
for as long as possible?
留得久一点?
How can we keep them in school beyond the age of 10 or 12
如何让他们在10或12岁后还留在学校
so that they don't join street gangs?
让他们远离街头帮派?
So that they are not hurt by drugs or crime?"
让他们远离毒品和犯罪?"
"How can we keep them safe at school?"―
"如何使他们安全地留在学校?"
An important question to ask. However,not enough.
这是个很重要的问题 但还不只如此
Marva Collins comes along and reframes the question.
Marva Collins重新定义这个问题
And her question becomes
她提出的问题是
"how can we cultivate the seed of greatness in our student?"
"我们如何培养学生 激发他们的潜能?"
And that,once again,made all the difference,
这问题改变了一切
because she saw the seed of greatness in each student.
因为她看到了每个学生的潜能
She saw the strength,the virtues in each single student.
她看到每个学生身上的优点和品德
A seed,a strength,a virtue,a competence
潜能 优点 品德 能力
that other teachers did not see,
这些是其他老师没看到的
because they did not ask this question;
因为他们没提出这个问题
because they asked,metaphorically speaking,
打个比方 他们只会问
"how many geometric shapes do you see on the screen?"
"你在屏幕上看到多少个几何图案?"
And they completely missed the children on the bus.
他们完全忽略了车上的孩子
They completely missed the seed of greatness.
完全忽略了学生的潜能
And when we don't see the seed of greatness,
如果我们看不见学生的潜能
when we don't water it and shed a light on it,
不去栽培它
it withers and dies,
它就会枯萎而死
which is unfortunately the fate of most human potential.
遗憾的是 大部分人类潜能都因此而被磨灭
Wherever we go,that is the fate of most human potential―
无论在哪 这都是大部分人类潜能的遭遇
interpersonally,relationships,in most organizations,
人与人之间 很多团体中
in most universities,in most individuals.
很多大学里或人们自己 这些潜能都因被忽视而磨灭
Questions make a difference,
疑问引起改变
which is why it is also important to ask
因此提问是非常重要的
the positive psychology question,
提出积极心理学的问题很重要
which is the salutogenic question:
也就是"健康创成"的问题
"What is source of health? What is the source of success?
"健康源于什么?成功源于什么?
What is the source of wellbeing?"
幸福源于什么?"
So that's the first reason. The second reason―
这是第一个原因 而第二个原因是
before I go to the second reason,
在谈第二个原因时
if Marva Collins is here today,
如果Marva Collins今天在场
here's the question she would be asking us:
那她会问我们这个问题:
"How can we cultivate the seed of greatness
"我们如何在于自身和家人中
in ourselves and families,
栽培伟大的种子
in our communities and organizations,
如何在在社区和团体中 栽培伟大的种子
in our nation and in our world?"
在国家和世界中呢"
When we ask this question-- this very important question,
当我们提出这个极为重要的问题
suddenly we see possibilities that we didn't see before.
就会看到之前没看到的潜能
Second reason for having positive psychology's field of study
第二个研究积极心理学的原因
and focusing on what works and focusing on
研究可行的事和
research in happiness,relationships and wellbeing
研究快乐 人际关系 幸福的原因
is because happiness does not spontaneously rise
是因为幸福不会因为驱除了忧愁
when take unhappiness away.
而自动增长
Now happiness and unhappiness,or happiness and neurosis,
幸福与忧愁 快乐与紧张
psychosis and depression,are interconnected,of course.
精神病与抑郁 都有很大的内在联系
It's very difficult to be happy
要快乐并不容易
if we are experiencing severe depression or anxiety.
如果我们感觉很压抑或焦虑
So they are certainly interconnected. However,
就是说他们必然是有关联的 然而
just getting rid of the anxiety and the depression will not in
单单摆脱焦虑与压抑并不会
and of itself make us happy,
使我们快乐
which is the conventional wisdom today,
这一点算是传统的常识
which is the conventional wisdom
是很多从业的心理学家
of many psychologists practicing psychologies―
会了解的一点常识
"Well,let's just get rid of that depression
"摆脱抑郁
and everything will be fine."
一切都会变好的"
It won't.
事实并非如此
The analogy to explain this is think about
解释这一点的一个例子是
the ability to enjoy food.
享受美食的能力
A gourmet meal.
美味大餐
Now if we have indigestion,it's very difficult to enjoy food.
如果我们消化不良 那很难享受美食
So yes,we first need to get rid of the indigestion.
因此我们得先治好消化不良
However,that in and of itself
然而 治好消化不良
does not guarantee us that we enjoy food.
不保证我们就能享受美食
We have to go out and eat the gourmet food to enjoy it.
要享受美味大餐 就得出去吃
Just getting rid of indigestion is not sufficient.
只是治愈消化不良远远不够
We need the next step.
还要做好下一步的事
In many ways you can look at most of our experiences,
可以从多方面来看我们的经验
psychological effective experiences on a continuum,
在心理连续谱上看有效心理经验
where some of them fall below the zero,
有时候会跌倒0以下
the negative experiences or the painful experiences
不愉快或痛苦的经历
and the positive or the pleasurable experiences
积极或愉快的经历
between the zero and the positive.
分别在0与正值之间
Neurosis,anger,anxiety,depression,psychosis―
紧张 愤怒 焦虑 压抑 精神病
to name a few-- on the negative side,the painful side;
这些消极和痛苦的方面
wellbeing,satisfaction,joy,excitement,happiness
幸福 满足 愉悦 兴奋 快乐
on the other side
属于另一方面
which is the side of positive psychology studies.
也就是积极心理学研究的方面
Again,getting rid of the negative
再强调一次 摆脱消极
does not guarantee us the positive,
不能保证我们变得积极
which is why already in the 1840s,
因此早在19世纪40年代
David Henry Thoreau (should be Henry David Thoreau),
梭罗
wrote that most men lead lives of quiet desperation.
认为 大多数人都活在沉默的压抑中
It's Ok. There's nothing really wrong.
这是没错的
But it's just somewhere there in the words of Pink Floyd
但平克弗洛伊德说过
"people are comfortably numb". Comfortably numb.
"人们在舒适地麻木" 舒适地麻木
Not enough. How can we get beyond that "comfortably numb"?
还不止如此 我们要怎样摆脱这种"舒适地麻木"?
How can we get beyond that "quiet desperation"?
要怎样摆脱"沉默的压抑"?
To excitement,to joy,to happiness?
得到振奋 快乐 幸福?
In order to do that,we need to cultivate these traits.
为了达到这目的 我们需用心经营这些情感因素
Once again,they don't spontaneously emerge
再说一次 幸福不会自动出现
once the painful experiences go away.
并不是没有痛苦就能感到幸福
And that is why we need positive psychology.
因此我们才需要积极心理学
Positive psychology essentially focuses on the health model,
积极心理学本质上就是健康模型
Salutogenesis.
健康本源学
What is the source of health,physical,psychological,emotional?
健康 生理 心理 情感之源是什么?
How do we get people to flourish,intellectually,emotionally,
我们如何让人们从智力上 情感上
psychologically,interpersonally,intra-personally?
心理上 人际关系上 人格上全面发展?
How do we get them to thrive beyond just getting rid
我们如何让他们全面发展 而不仅仅是帮他们摆脱
of what is not working in their lives?
生活中不如意的事?
And under that model we see,to extremes on many levels.
根据该模型 我们在许多层面上都走了极端
Here,the first level:
第一个层次:
do we focus on weaknesses,
我们是否重视缺点
which is the disease model,say let's get rid of weaknesses?
也就是疾病模型所说的我们要摆脱的缺点
Or do we focus on strength?
或者说 我们是否专注于优点?
While you ask people this question,
当你问别人这个问题
and this was done by the Gallup organization.
盖洛普组织做了这项研究
A poll-- global poll,
一项全球民意调查显示
whether it's in Japan,China,United States or Europe:
无论是在日本 中国 美国或欧洲
most people think that it's more important
大多数人认为 如果要成功
to focus on their weaknesses if they are to succeed.
注重自己的缺点比优点更重要
Big mistake.
大错特错
The people who focus primarily,not only-- remember the "also"―
那些同样注重自己优点的人
who shift the pendulum,who focus more on their strength,
改变那个比率的人 更注重优点的人
are not only happier,they are also,on the long run,
不仅更开心 从长远来看他们也
more successful.
更成功
It applies to leadership as well.
这同样适用于领导能力
Positive psychology says let's focus also
积极心理学认为 我们至少
on our strength at least as much.
注重优点的程度要和注重缺点一样多
In an organization,as well as on the individual level,
无论是组织还是个人自身
are we focusing most on overcoming deficiencies
我们最注重的是克服缺点
or building the competencies―
还是培养才能?
what we are good at-- and getting better at it?
我们擅长什么 并是否取得了进步?
What our natural inclination,individually or organizationally―
个人或组织的自然倾向是什么
do we focus on that and then build on that?
我们是否更注重自己的自然倾向?
Again,tie to success as well as wellbeing,
注重健康的同时也要注重幸福
if we are more toward the positive side.
如果我们是较为积极的话
How do we live our lives?
我们如何活出自己的精彩?
Running away from painful experiences?
如何摆脱痛苦的经历
Or actively seeking pleasure?
或积极寻找快乐?
Running away from unhappiness?
如何摆脱悲伤?
Or adhering to the Declaration (Declaration of Independence)
还是遵循宣言(独立宣言)行事
and pursuing happiness?
追求幸福?
Now that may look quite similar-- for example,
举个例 下面的两种人看起来非常相似
someone may be working 80 hours a week,
某人可能每周工作80小时
running away from something-- running away from issues at home,
他习惯逃避 逃避家事
running away from dealing intra-personal issues
逃避处理私事
and then may look exactly the same as the person
但他看起来却和下面这种人一样
who works 80 hours a week and who's extremely passionate
她每周工作80小时 对工作
about what she does.
充满热情
May look the same but from the inside,they feel very different.
表面看来他们一样 但他们的内心感觉很不同
One is the disease model:
一种是疾病模型
let's run away from what is not working.
让我们逃避不如意的事
The other is the health model:
另一种是健康模型
let's pursue my passions,what I love to do.
让我们追求激情 追求喜欢做的事
The disease model,the optimum level is the zero:
对疾病模型而言 最优水平是零
let's just be Ok; let's just not hurt.
我们都平平安安 别受伤就好了
And again,that's important to get rid of hurt.
再说一次 免受伤害是非常重要的
It's important to get rid of depression.
摆脱抑郁非常重要
But with the health model,they are saying that's not enough;
但依健康模式来看 这是不够的
let's go beyond that.
让我们超越那种程度
Let's go to the excitement,to the fun.
让我们兴奋起来 快乐起来
Because the ideal is not just a tensionless state.
因为理想状态并不只是放松
It is the creative tension.
它是创造性的紧张状态
We'll talk about it. We'll read about it.
我们会谈到它 会读到相关的文章
When we do "flow". Flow is the state where we are excited,
当我们"沉迷"之时 那就是我们感到兴奋
where we are engaging what we are doing,
为所做之事着迷的状态
where it's much more than being "comfortably numb".
那样大大超越了"舒适地麻木"
In fact,it's a little bit uncomfortable.
事实上 在那种状态下会有点不舒适
It's being outside of our comfort zone.
那是在我们舒适区之外的
It's being in our stretch zone―
可算是我们的延伸地带
not the panic zone,where it hurts-- the stretch zone,
不是会让人受伤的恐慌地带 而是延伸地带
where there is excitement,where there's some nervousness.
其中有兴奋 还有点紧张
There is also growth there.
还可能会有成长
So what do you want?
所以 你的目的是什么?
Where do you want to go? What do you want to pursue?
你想去哪?你要追求什么?
Do you want to run away from pleasure-- run away from pain?
你想逃避愉悦吗?想逃避痛苦吗?
Do you want to run away from unhappiness?
你想逃避不快乐吗?
Or do you want to pursue happiness and pleasure?
还是你想追求幸福和快乐?
Do you want to focus primarily on your deficiencies
你更注重你的不足之处
or your weaknesses?
或缺点吗?
Or your strength?
还是更注重优点?
What is the optimum? what is the ideal?
什么是最有利的选择?什么是理想状态?
Is there a glass ceiling-- the zero?
有无形的障碍 零点吗?
Or can it go on and on―
还是可以继续
more excitement,more enjoyment,more passion?
寻找到更多的刺激 享受 激情?
Now there's something frightening about the health model.
有一些关于健康模型的可怕说法
Because there is no limit and there is less prescription there
因为没有界线 如今它的使用程度
certainly today than in the disease model.
也远比疾病模型少
Positive psychology,
积极心理学
the field of health psychology is in infancy.
健康心理学的研究还处于初级阶段
There's much more research,
而且有更多的研究是关于
much more advice on how to get rid of depression
如何摆脱抑郁
and how do I pursue my strength.
如何发展自己的优点
But fortunately,again,this is why positive psychology as
但幸运的是 这就是为什么要学习积极心理学
a network of scholars applying themselves
大量的学者致力于
to these ideas and ideals. It's so important
研究这些观点 它意义非凡
because today you'll see throughout the semester
因为今天你们会看到整个学期的概览
that there are so many more tools that we can apply to our lives,
有很多方法可以让我们的生活质量
to go beyond the zero.
达到正值
That's not all.
这还不是全部
So I said there are three reasons.
我说过有三个原因
It's about where we focus,focus creates reality;
关键在于我们侧重点 侧重点创造现实
it's about happiness is not just a negation of unhappiness;
快乐并不只是对不快乐的否定
the third reason why positive psychology is important
积极心理学之所以重要的第三个原因是
is because positive psychology and the areas
积极心理学领域
that we study and more importantly,
还有与积极心理学
apply within the field of positive psychology,
相关的领域
do not just take us from the zero to the positive.
不仅让我们从零点上升到正值
They also help us deal with the negative.
积极心理学还帮助我们处理消极情绪
They help us deal with anxiety,
帮助我们处理焦虑不安
depression and painful experiences and emotions.
处理抑郁和痛苦的经历 及情感问题
When we cultivate the positive,
当我们培养出积极性
we are essentially focusing on prevention.
我们本质上是自我防御的
Let me explain.
我解释一下
What has been found over the last 10 years
过去10年多时间的研究发现
and a little bit longer is the most effective way of actually
处理我们不断增加的抑郁病例
dealing with a rising levels of depression in our culture,
个体的抑郁或焦虑
with individual depression or anxiety is actually not to
最有效方法是
focus on the depression and anxiety directly―
不要直接专注于抑郁和焦虑
that is important as well.
这点也很重要
It is found that the most effective way
事实证明 处理这种现象
of dealing with this phenomenon was actually
最有效的方法是
to cultivate the positive,to cultivate personal strengths,
培养积极性和个人优点
to cultivate and identify one's passions,
培育激情
to ask a question such as "what is meaningful to me in my life?
提出这种问题"我人生中什么是有意义的?
What's my purpose? Why am I here?
我的目的是什么?我为什么在这里?
What do I really,really want to do once I graduate?"
毕业后我真正想做的是什么?"
People who ask these questions
提出这些问题
and spend time on these questions,
并认真思考这些问题的人
are much more likely to begin a quest
所追求的
that is not the avoid of painful emotions―
不是避免痛苦
no quest is―
而是
but the quest is more enjoyable,more pleasurable,
追求更多快乐
more meaningful and also,more successful as it turns out.
使生活更有意义 更成功
But more importantly,more successful in
更重要的是 我将"更成功"
what I call the "the ultimate currency"―
称之为"终极货币"
just as the currency of happiness and wellbeing.
正如快乐货币和幸福货币一样
The reason is because there are two different approaches
究其原因 是因为有两种不同的方法
to deal with illness: one,the positive psychological approach is
对付疾病 一是积极心理学方法
that the illness is the absence of health,
它指的是 疾病相当于不健康
as opposed to health is the absence of illness.
相对地 健康等于没疾病
I mean,think about the disease model.
我们想一下疾病模式
The disease model is "we are sick because we are ill"―
疾病模式是 "我们感到不适是因为生病了"
do you listen to that? We are sick because we are ill.
听到吗?我们病了是因为我们在生病
That was very profound.
真的很深奥
You should think about it for a while here.
你们可能要好好想一下这句话
I'll let a time just to marinate it little bit so that you can.
可能要给点时间大家消化这话
Let me start that again.
我重新说一遍
If we take away the illness,then we become healthy.
如果治好病 就会变得健康
That's the model,the conventional model.
这是个传统的模型
Take away the illness. You'll become healthy. It's good.
把病治好 就会变得健康 这很好
The positive psychological model is slightly different.
积极心理学模型略有不同
It is
它说的是
"you are ill because you don't have enough health in your life,
"你生病了 是因为你的生活还不够健康
because you are not pursuing those things that make you healthy".
因为你不去追求那些让你健康的东西"
And what make you healthy?
什么使你健康?
The things I spoke about before: pursuing meaning,purpose;
这我之前已谈过 追求有意义的生活 人生的目的
cultivating healthy relationships.
培养健康的人际关系
If we don't have these things,that's when the illness comes in.
如果不具备这些 疾病就会趁虚而入
Now the difference between the two models,
两种模型
the health model and the disease model
健康模型和疾病模型的差异
is more than just semantic.
不仅仅是语义上的
Here is Abraham Maslow talking about neurosis,
这是Abraham Maslow所说的神经官能症
"Neurosis is a falling short of what one could have been
"神经官能症描述的是人能变成怎样
and even one could say,of what one should have been,
或是他该变成怎样
biologically speaking that is
从生理上来说就是是
if one had grown and developed in an unimpeded way.
一个人是否能顺利地成长和发展
Human and personal possibilities have been lost.
人类和个人的潜能已经消失
The world has been narrowed and so has consciousness.
世界逐渐缩小 意识也是
Capacities have been inhibited."
能力也被抑制"
Let me explain what he means here.
我来解释一下这话的意思
What he means is that we are ill because we do not cultivate
他是说 我们正在生病 是因为我们没有
what we are about enough.
尽力做好我们本该做到的事
We do not become self-actualized.
我们没做到自我实现
We don't do what we are supposed to do.
没做到该做的
We diminish ourselves and that's when we become ill.
我们削弱自身力量 因此才会生病
That's when we are unwell.
才会不适
This is very different from the disease model that says,
这和疾病模型所说的有很大不同
"Ok,you are unwell. Deal with that illness."
"好 你不舒服 那就治病去吧"
What he's saying: "No. You are unwell.
他说的是:"不 你不舒服
Focus on your health. Strengthen your health.
要注重健康 加强你的健康
Because you are ill,
因为你病了
because you are not focusing enough on your health."
因为你没有注重健康"
He calls that,and I quote,
他将这称为
"a failure of personal growth".
"个人成长的失败"
That's when we experience neurosis.
如果我们感到焦虑
When we don't cultivate ourselves enough,
如果我们不注重培养自己的能力
we don't cultivate our relationships enough,that's when we fail.
不注重培养自己的人际关系 就会失败
And what the positive psychology is all about is precisely that―
积极心理学研究的是关于
cultivating personal growth,working on the positive.
培育自身成长和积极性
And we work on the positive on what comes of this side
我们研究积极性 它处于这一边
of the graph that you saw up there.
大家可以在这上面看到
On the positive side,when we cultivate these things,
在积极的一方 当我们注重培养这些情感因素
it also helps us deal much better
就会助于我们更好地处理
with the negative when dead arises.
消极因素
I want to quote Martin Seligman,
我想引用Martin Seligman的话
who talks about precisely this idea:
他说过这样一句话
"In the last decade
"在过去的十年
psychologists have become concerned with prevention.
心理学家关心的都是预防的问题
How can we prevent problems like depression
怎样才能预防像抑郁症这样的心理问题
or substance abuse or schizophrenia in young people
或年轻人中常出现的药物滥用或精神分裂症
who are genetically vulnerable or who live in worlds
谁天生敏感脆弱 谁又是
that nurture these problems?
制造这些问题的人?
How can we prevent murderous schoolyard violence in children
如何防止校园暴力
who have access to weapons,poor parental supervision,
这些暴力事件通常是由掌握武器 缺乏父母监管
and a mean streak?"
或受到教唆的孩子引起的
Now he's asking this question and the disease model
他问了这个问题 根据疾病模型
response to this is we need to help them deal
我们需要帮助他们直接
directly with depression,
处理抑郁症
with their anxiety and with their unhappiness
还有他们的焦虑和忧愁
so that we can prevent all these social ills―
才能防止所有这些社会弊病
whether it's violence,whether it's unhappiness.
无论是暴力还是不快乐
What he's saying here is the following:
他是这么说的
"What we have learned over fifty years is that the disease model
"五十多年的经验告诉我们 疾病模型
does not move us closer to the prevention
不能让我们更有力地预防
of these serious problems.
这些严重问题
Indeed the major strides in prevention
事实上 在预防方面取得的重大进展
have largely come from a perspective focused
基本上来自一个观点
on systematically building competency,not correcting weakness."
也就是注重培养能力 而非改正错误"
In other words,the health model:
换句话说 健康模型倡导
let's work on competencies.
培养能力
Let's work on strength. Let's work on relationship.
增强自身长处 改善人际关系
Let's help them identify something meaningful in their life,
帮助人们找到对自己人生有意义的事
their passion.
和他们的热情所在
And that's how we will,over time,
那就是我们将要致力做到的
also help what comes off on the negative side.
同样对克服消极因素 有所帮助
Health model versus the disease model
健康模型与疾病模型不同
that goes directly to deal with the disease.
疾病模型提倡直接处理疾病的
Now again,Seligman is not saying "to the exclusion of";
Seligman不是说"排除"疾病模型
he's saying "also".
而是说也可以用健康模型
He continues,
他还说
"We have discovered that there are human strengths
我们已发现有些人类的力量
that act as buffers against mental illness:
能抵抗心理疾病
courage,future-mindedness,optimism,interpersonal skill,
勇气 未来规划 乐观 人际技巧
faith,work ethic,hope,honesty,perseverance,
信念 职业道德 希望 诚实 毅力
the capacity for flow and insight,to name several.
专注及洞察力 诸如此类
We'v e shown that learning optimism prevents depression
研究证实 乐观可帮助儿童和成人
and anxiety in children and adults,
预防抑郁和焦虑
roughly halving their incidence over the next 2 years.
使未来两年的发病率降低一半
Similarly,I believe that if we wish to prevent drug abuse
同样 如果我们要防止
in teenagers who grow up in a neighborhood
青少年受不良的社会环境影响
that puts them at risk,
而滥用药物的情况
the effective prevention is not remedial.
但预防的效果不佳
Rather,it consists of identifying and amplifying
相反 它认定并放大了这个事实
the strengths that these teens already have."
就是青少年们已滥用药物"
It's exactly what Marva Collins did:
Marva Collins所做的就是
focused on the health and cultivated it,
注重健康并用心栽培它
watered it and shed a light to it,realized it.
浇水 给予阳光并时刻关注它
We'll talk about all these ideas throughout the course.
对这些观点的探讨将贯穿整个课程
What health model does―
健康模式能做的就是-
this is the theme we go through all the course
这是我们这堂课着重讲的内容
is cultivate capacity.
培养能力
It cultivates the capacity to deal
培养我们处理
with the negatives when these arrive―
消极因素的能力
whether it's negative and painful experiences in relationships,
无论是人际关系上的消极和痛苦经历
or in ourselves.
还是我们自身的
What does that mean? Let me draw two analogies.
那意味着什么 我为大家做两个类比
Cultivating capacity is about creating a strong psychological
培养能力就是创造一个强大的
immune system.
心理免疫系统
These are the words of Nathaniel Branden.
这是Nathaniel Branden的观点
Psychological immune system.
心理学免疫系统
What happens when we have a strong physical immune system?
如果我们有强大的生理免疫系统会怎样?
Does it mean we don't get ill?
这是否意味着我们不会生病?
Of course not. We do.
当然不是 还是会生病
But it means that we get ill less often and when we do get sick,
但这意味着我们不会常生病 就算病了
we recover more promptly.
也能恢复得更快
This is exactly what cultivating strength,
这就是培养的力量
optimism,sense of purpose,meaning,mindfulness―
乐观 追求 意义 规划
this is exactly what these characteristics do.
正是这些因素的作用
They enlarge transform―
他们会放大并改变
the way we see,the way we experience the world,
我们看待和体验世界的方式
enlarge the capacity of the form and
让我们突破框架 引发潜能
that's we are better able to deal the inevitable difficulties.
使我们能更好地应对不可避免的困难
And there are inevitable difficulties.
不可避免的困难的确存在
No life is completely immune to those.
没有谁的人生是一帆风顺的
So it strengthens our immune system.
它可以增强我们的免疫系统
And another analogy we can use is of an engine.
另一个类比是关于引擎的
If we have a small engine,
如果我们用的引擎很小
and we have to pull the car up a steep hill,a difficult hill,
想把车开上一个陡峭崎岖的山坡
the engine is more likely to collapse,to blow up.
引擎很容易损毁 爆炸
Whereas If our engine is large,
但如果我们的引擎够大
we are much more likely to get up that hill,
要上那山就容易得多
and to do it gracefully with relative ease.
不费吹灰之力就能做到
So what we are doing: we cultivate the positive;
所以我们在做的是 培养积极性
we are strengthening our,metaphorically speaking,
按那个比喻来说 我们正在增强
psychological "engine";
心理"引擎"
and we are better able to deal with the negative to zero,
我们能够更好将负值转化为零
not to mention the fact that we are also able to become happier.
更别说还能变得更快乐
Because happiness does not just come spontaneously
因为快乐不会自发而来
when we negate unhappiness.
不会因为消除了忧愁 就变得快乐
I want to go back to our local village.
我想说说我们这里的事
So remember last time
记得上次
I put up the article by the Crimson (Harvard Crimson magazine)
我提出的《哈佛克里姆森》杂志里的文章
that was unfortunately I couldn't find
很可惜我找不到
a more recent one-- that was 2004?
更近期一点的 那是2004年的?
But the situation is rather similar today.
但今天的情况非常相似
And one of the things that the Crimson article said is that
那篇文章提到的一点是
we need to put more resources into mental health at Harvard.
我们需要为哈佛学生的心理健康投入更多
And that's important,I agree.
这点很重要的 我非常赞同
However,it's only part of the picture.
这只是其中一点
in some different places as well-- not only,as well.
投入到其他一些地方
Because it's just not enough to put these resources in places
因为只是投入资源
that help us deal with our depression and anxiety
帮助我们应对抑郁 焦虑和忧愁
and unhappiness directly.
是远远不够的
It is also important to put these resources in places
同样重要的是 投入资源
that help us cultivate capacity,
帮助我们培养自身能力
the capacity to deal with these difficulties and hardships
应对困难和艰辛的能力
when they arise and they will arise.
这些困难一直存在并会继续出现的
In other words,there has to be more resources put in places
换句话说 必须在以下方面投入更多资源
such as helping students identify their passions
例如帮助学生发掘
when they come here,
自己的兴趣
helping students identify their sense of meaning in life,
帮助学生发现人生的意义
helping students identify what they
使他们明确自己
really,really,really want to do,
真正想做的事
helping students overcome the pull,
帮助他们克服那种诱惑
the external pull that is often there,
身边常出现的诱惑
taking them away from their core,
会让他们偏离自己的道路
helping them chip away those limitations,
还有凿掉那些束缚
those voices,helping students identify who they really are,
摆脱杂念 帮助他们找到自己的真实个性
helping students identify their strengths
还有帮助学生了解自己的强项
and pursuing those while here at Harvard.
并在哈佛实现一切
All these capabilities,
所有这些能力
all these skills or skills that are mostly―
所有这些技能 大多数都
and I'm not just talking about Harvard―
我不只是说哈佛
globally-- not taught in schools.
而是全球范围内 没有一所学校会教这些技能
And we need to teach them.
所以我们需要教他们
This is not to say that what is going at Harvard
这并不是说哈佛现在
with numerous resources that we do have here is not important.
正投入大量资源的方面不重要
It is very important.
这些方面都非常重要的
Just take a small example:
举个小例子
the Bureau of Study Counsel.
学习咨询处
I don't know how many of you have used that resource.
我不知道你们有多少人利用过该资源
I've used it as an undergrad.
我念本科时已开始接触它
I still use it now,doing some work with them.
至今还在与他们一起做某些工作
I did some work with them last year.
去年我与他们合作过
And they are wonderful.
他们真的很棒
And at the same time,we also need to cultivate the positive,
同时 我们还需要培养积极性
to think more of the zero to the positive side
探究如何让我们从零点升到正直
of the equation as well.
该如何做
And this is what positive psychology does
这就是积极心理学的作用
and I hope this is what 1504 to some extent will help do.
我希望1504号课程在一定程度上会有帮助
To summarize,
总之
"the message of the positive psychology movement
"积极心理学运动提醒我们
is to remind our field that it has been deformed.
这个领域已与过去不同
Psychology is not just the study of disease,weakness,and damage
心理学不仅是对疾病 弱点和伤害进行研究
it also is the study of strength and virtue,
它也研究优点和美德
Treatment is not just fixing what is wrong;
治疗不只是修复错误
it also is building what is right.
同时也要塑造正确的东西
Psychology is not just about illness or health;
心理学关注的不仅仅是疾病或健康状况
it is about work,education,insight,love,growth,and play.
还包括工作 教育 洞察力 爱 成长和玩乐
And in this quest for what is best,
在追求理想状态时
positive psychology does not rely on wishful thinking,
积极心理学不会盲目主观
self-deception,or hand waving;
或自欺欺人 或敷衍了事
instead,it tries to adapt what is best in the scientific method
相反 它尝试用最科学的方法来探究
to the unique problems that human behavior presents
极其复杂的人类行为所表现出来的
in all its complexity."
特殊问题"
It's about bridging the Ivory tower and the Main Street
还涉及到如何将学校与社会连接起来
in the area that I believe is the most important one
这个我认为最重要的领域
and talks to each and every one of us.
对我们来说都有意义
I want to move on now.
好 我继续说下去
I want to move on to the next selective lectures―
我想先说说下一节关于选择的课程
two or two and a half lectures,
两节或两节半课
where I am going to be talking about
我将会谈到
the basic premises of this course.
本课程的基本前提
As I said earlier,
正如我刚才所说
this course is not a survey course of positive psychology.
本课程并不是积极心理学的调研课
It's very selective. It's about the question of questions.
这是关于选择"问题中的问题"的
What can help us individuals,
有什么可以帮助我们个人
what can help our community become happier-- not happy,happier.
帮助我们的社会更快乐 不是快乐 是更快乐
So by the end of these three months semester,
三个月后 期末时
you are happier than you were before.
你会变得更快乐
You are from now,you'll be hopefully happier than you were
到学期末 你很可能比现在的你
at the end of the semester.
更快乐
And so on and so on.
越来越快乐
So what are the basic premises?
基本前提是什么?
Where am I coming here when I think about this course?
备课时我想和大家说些什么呢?
Well what I want to do is to share with you
我想为大家介绍
the five basic premises.
五个基本前提
And these premises are going to be presented as something and―
介绍这些前提 要从
essentially it's opposite.
它的对立面说起
So that were clear from the outset:
下面这些问题非常明确
where we are coming from,where I am coming from,
我们从哪里来 我从哪里来
where the teaching staff is coming from―
教学人员从哪里来
and also so that we can build the foundation of the course.
了解这些后我们就能建立本课程的基础
Remember I talk those of you who were here the first time:
记得一开始我就跟你们说过
this course is built like a spiral
这课程就像个螺旋
Everything is intra-connected,
内部的一切都是相关的
what I talked about in the first class is connected to
第一节课讲到的内容
what I'm going to talk about today,
与今天要谈的课题有关
is going to be connected to lecture 19.
也和第19课有关
So in many ways the premises,
从许多方面来看 这个前提
coupled with what we discussed in the first two lectures,
跟我们开头的两节课有关
build the foundation of that spiral,
会建立这个螺旋的基础
upon which everything else will be built.
那其他一切就更容易建起来
So here are the five basic premises.
这里有五个基本前提
I'll go through them briefly now and elaborate on each
我会先简短地介绍一下 再逐个阐述
in the next couple of lectures,interweaving them
在接下来的几节课里 会分别对它们
with studies,research as well as applications.
进行学习 研究 和应用
First,this course as I mentioned first is about bridge building:
正如我开始时提到的 这课程是关于搭建桥梁的
bridge building among disciplines,eclectic,
搭建学科之间的桥梁 广集思源
and bridge building in terms of academia and Main street.
并搭建学术界与社会之间的桥梁
the specialization is very often dominant in academia.
专业化常在学术界占主导地位
The approach of this course,
本课程的做法
with all its challenges,is the opposite.
正好相反
Once again I wouldn't be teaching this class,
如果我认为没有改变的可能
if I didn't change is possible.
就不会教这节课
There is a lot of research in psychology,
心理学的研究有很多
a lot of evidence that shows how difficult change is.
很多证据显示 改变是非常困难的事
So I will argue that change is possible,
我认为改变是可能的
whether it's individual change,
无论是个人变化
organizational change.
还是组织变革
And we'll start to look at how it's possible.
我们将探讨为什么是可能的
Just the very basic level of the spiral.
这只是整个螺旋的最基本层次
We have an entire week just devoted to change.
我们本周只讨论"改变"
We will elaborate on that:
我们会详细讨论
techniques,methods,tools.
技巧 方法 工具
Third,premise related to the first
第三 这个前提与
internal factors primarily determine happiness―
决定幸福的内部因素有关
this is what I'm going to argue for―
这是我要讨论的
is opposed to happiness which is primarily function
与决定幸福的
of external circumstances.
外部环境无关
Not saying that the external circumstances are not important,
并不是说 外部环境不重要
we should focus also on improving them,bettering them,
我们同样应该注重改善外部环境
whether for ourselves,for society at large.
无论是我们自己 或对整个社会
However,happiness primarily―
然而 幸福主要
not only,primarily―is dependent on how we perceive the world,
在于我们如何看待世界
on the form,on our interpretation,on our perception.
社会习俗规条 我们理性和感性上的认知
Human nature must be obeyed
"只能顺从人性"
This,in many ways,
在各个方面
captures conflict that has gone throughout human history,
这酿成了历史上许多冲突
whether you look at politics,whether you look at religion,
无论是政治上 还是宗教上
whether you look at philosophy as well as today,psychology.
无论是哲学 还是心理学
How do we look at human nature?
我们如何看待人性?
Is human nature flawed and therefore needs to be perfected?
是人性有缺陷 因此需要进一步完善吗?
Or is human nature flawed maybe something we don't like
还是尽管我们不喜欢人性中的缺陷
but we need to accept it and work with it?
也必须接受它?
I'm going to argue for the latter of what I just said,
我会谈到后者
for the fact that human nature needs to be obeyed
就是说我们必须顺从于人性
with all its flaws,with all its shortcomings,
接受它所有的缺陷和优点
as opposed to attempting to perfect it
而不是试图从心理层面上
on the psychological level.
完善它
We'll get to that next time.
我们下节课再说这话题
Controversial,
颇具争议的是
the very important foundation of mental health and wellbeing.
精神健康和幸福的重要基础
And finally,
最后
what I am going to argue for is that happiness isn't ought to be
我想说的是 幸福不应该只是
the ultimate end which we pursue and that is also a moral claim,
我们追求的最终目标 还是一种道德追求
as opposed to happiness just being another secondary pursuit
而不是一种普通的追求
and there are pursuits―
但也有些追求
there are higher,more important,more moral than that.
是更高级 更重要 更高尚的
Once again,may sound controversial.
这一点也颇具争议
I'll try reconcile the disease,
我也会涉及疾病
the unhappiness that you may experience thinking about that.
和大家也许关心过的忧愁
Again,more on that next time.
同样 这留待下节课再讲
So let me begin with bridge building.
现在我们先从搭建"桥梁"说起
Here I am going back to what I talked about right
说回第一节课开始时
at the very beginning of the first lecture.
谈到的问题
The idea of bridging Ivory tower and Main Street.
也就是 搭起学校与社会之间的桥梁的想法
There are many people in academia,outside academia,
学术界内外 都有很多人
who divide the world essentially into two.
将世界一分为二
They talked about the real world that is outside,
他们将外面的世界看成是现实
that is dirty,impure,profane versus academia,
是肮脏的 不洁 被亵渎的 而学术界
which is lofty,idealistic,sacred.
则是崇高的 有理想的 神圣的
Sacred versus the profane.
神圣与亵渎
This distinction hurts.
这种区分带来伤害
It hurts academia and hurts people who are outside of academia.
它同时伤害了学术界及非学术界的人
Alfred North Whitehead,the philosopher:
哲学家Alfred North Whitehead
"The careful shielding of a university
"大学小心翼翼地将我们
from the activities of the world around us
与外界活动隔开
is the best way to chill interest and to defeat progress.
这样最容易打击学习兴趣 阻碍学习进步
Celibacy does not suit a university.
大学不适合独身生活
It must mate itself with action."
必须要与身边的人互动
This is very important for university.
这点对大学生活非常重要
talked about a second psychology.
他当时提到另一种心理学
He said second psychology is a psychology
他说另一种心理学就是
that leaves the labs that draws on the research done in the labs
抛开实验室的研究
that is important and meaningful,
实验室研究意义重大
however,doesn't only focus on that.
但不只是注重这种研究
It goes out to the outside world,
而是走到外面的世界
interacts,gets its hand and mind dirty,
与外界互动 接触那些"肮脏"事物
does work outside and then applies its work
在外面工作 并吸取经验
and learns from "the dirty experiences"
从"肮脏经验"中学习
and brings it back to the lab
将得到的经验带回实验室
and so on and so on in an upward spiral.
诸如此类 就像一个上升的螺旋
He called it the important second psychology,
他称之为重要的另一种心理学
which is what Alfred North Whitehead is also talking about.
这也是Alfred North Whitehead所提倡的
Now you may be sitting here
现在你们来到这里
and most of you aren't going to academia.
且大多数人将来都不会进入学术界
And you are thinking to yourself,
你可能会想
"Ok,fine. So university,academia must make itself with action.
"好 学术界要结合实践做研究
What does it have to do with me? How is this relevant to me?"
那与我有何关系?我们的联系在哪?"
Not only is it relevant to you,it has everything to do with you.
它不仅与你有联系 它与你息息相关
And here's why.
下面就是原因
What the world needs,
世界最需要的
more than anything else,is practical idealists.
不是其他什么 就是务实的理想主义者
For 6 years,I was a resident tutor in Leverett House
我做过6年莱弗里特宿舍的住校导师
when I was a graduate student and then I also started to teach.
我研究生在读时 就开始任教
And what struck me most about conversations that I had,
在与学生的交谈中 让我印象最深的是
either in Leverett or other houses,
无论是在莱弗里特宿舍或其他地方
were students is their sense of mission,your sense of mission,
学生们的使命感 你们的使命感
your desire to do good,
你们对成功的渴望
to make the world a better place.
让世界变得更美好的愿望
And as I followed many of the students after they graduate,
据我了解 很多学生毕业后
whether the students who work with me here as undergrads
无论是与我一起工作
or students who I tutored,
还是我辅导的学生
when I followed the path,it wasn't just empty words.
当我了解他们的前路 并不是些空话
These students went ahead and did wonderful things,
这些学生勇往直前 做了非常棒的事
whether it was right out of college,
无论是校外校内的
whether it was once they established themselves,
无论他们是否刚建立起自身
but there was always this,the back of their mind,
但可以确定的是 他们潜藏的思想
very often fore of their minds,
很多时候会涌现出来
"How can I make this world a better place?"
"我怎样才能使这个世界变得更美好?"
Passionate. Idealistic.
充满热情 理想化
Good-- in the deep sense,good.
美好 极其美好
This desire to make a difference
渴望改变世界
come into just about all students.
是所有学生都有的想法
There are many people who talk about this generation
很多人认为这一代人
as the "ME" generation: all I care about,
以自我为中心
all this generation cares about is
这一代人只关心
"well,let me just make more money",
"赚更多的钱"
"let me just get a bigger house",
"买大一点的房子"
"let me just be more successful and accrue more eclats,
"更成功 取得更高荣誉
more prestige".
变得更有威望"
This is a false stereotype.
这是一种错误的刻板印象
Yes,eclats,prestige,money is important.
是的 荣誉 威望 金钱是重要的
It's important to most people in the world.
这对大多数人来说都很重要
A big deal.
甚至是最重要的
But were these people who have these stereotypes―
但有这些刻板印象的人
were they (?) is that they see just that?
他们只看到这些是最重要的吗?
And they don't see the desire to make a difference.
他们并不渴望改变世界
1800 students at Harvard each year,
每年哈佛有
about 1800 students are members of
约1800名学生是
PBHA (Phillips Brooks House Association).
PBHA(菲利普斯布鲁克斯楼协会)的成员
That's not all.
不仅如此
There are other students who outside PBHA and who volunteer.
还有一些没加入PBHA的学生甘当志愿者
Just about every single one of you.
几乎所有人都是
At least if we look at the statistics,
看一下统计数据
just about every single one of you,
你们每个人
very soon,
很快
after you leave Harvard,will join an organization,
离开哈佛后 都将加入公司
whether--it could be your primary job or not―
无论它是否你的主要工作
an organization that is a social enterprise,
这个组织是个社会企业
not for profit,something to better the world.
非盈利机构 只为贡献社会而存在的
You'll be on boards of such organizations.
你会加入这样一个组织
You'll donate money to such organizations.
你会捐钱给这些组织
Harvard grads are generous with their time,
哈佛毕业生一向慷慨 无论是对时间
with their money,with their efforts,
还是金钱和努力
whether the business school,the law school,
无论是商学院 法学院
college,Med school,Ed school―
医学院 教育学院
you give a lot,because you care.
你对社会贡献甚多 是因为你在乎
Again whether it's money,whether it's time-- usually both.
无论是要贡献金钱还是时间 通常两者都要
False stereotypes.
都是成见
There are also false stereotypes about Americans.
关于美国人也有些成见
Americans,empirically speaking―
凭经验来说 美国人
just empirically speaking about the Harvard students,
或只是说哈佛学生
looking the trends and statistics-- empirically speaking,
根据发展趋势和统计
Americans are the most generous people in the world.
美国人是世界上最慷慨的人
Not just because they have more money to give,
不仅仅是因为他们更富有
yes,Americans have more money to give
的确 美国人更富有
and they give a lot more money,
他们常捐钱
whether it's in food,whether it's in medical aid.
无论是在扶贫或医疗救助方面
Americans also spend the most time-- this is a research done (?)―
有研究证实 美国人也花最多时间
Americans spend the most time out of any other people
比其他任何人所花的时间都多
in the world volunteering in average four hours a week,
平均每周有四个小时做志愿者的工作
volunteering outside their job which may also have
做与自身工作无关的善事
a social objective more than any other people in the world.
他们比世界上其他人更具社会目标
Once again,false stereotypes about this wonderful country.
对于这个美好国家的成见
And this is wonderful.
这里很美好
This is wonderful to see,wonderful to be here,
能来到这里是件美好的事
whether it's Harvard,whether it's America-- a real privilege.
无论是在哈佛 还是在美国 真的很荣幸
You see,many of you,
你们许多人
not far from now,you will be in influential positions.
不久将会身居要职
Will you be able to do a lot of good
你们能够做善事吗
in a for-profit organization,not for profit organization,
在一个非营利机构里行善
on the board of your previous school,
在你母校的董事会
with your money,with your time?
贡献金钱和时间
However―
然而
and here is the however―
这是个原因
I've met many grad students with me
我与许多研究生相处过
or students when I was a tutor
或当导师时的学生
who express their frustration to me.
学生曾跟我谈及他们的困扰
They said to me,"You know,
他们曾对我说 "你知道
I had all the good intentions in the world.
我曾有世界上最良好的意愿
I have all the good intentions in the world. I want to do good.
我有最善良的心 想为世界作贡献
I've donated my time,my money.
我奉献出时间和金钱
But I feel that something is missing.
但还是觉得若有所失
I feel that I've fallen short of my potential
我觉得我能改变世界的能力
to really make a difference."
越来越弱了"
Why? Because good will and idealism,
为什么呢?因为美好的意愿和理想主义
while necessary,they are not sufficient.
虽然必要 但却是不够的
Not enough.
远远不够
Because very often,with very good intentions,
因为很多时候 即使有很好的意愿
we may fall short of what we are capable of doing,
我们的能力还是有限
or in some situations,even hurt more than help.
或在某些情况下 我们带来的伤害多于帮助
And we'll look at some of these studies,
有一些研究表明
hopefully still today,
即使到了今天仍有
with very good intentions actually hurt more they helped.
想做好事的人却好心干坏事
Psychologists for decades had very good intentions
数十年来的心理学家都有很好的意愿
about helping at risk population.
想帮助高危人群
A lot of money-- millions,millions of dollars went into that.
大量的金钱-数百万美元投资在研究上
With very little effect.
但收效甚微
Why? Because they didn't ask the question
为什么呢?因为他们没有提出这样的问题
that they needed to ask,which was,in that particular case,
这特定情况下 他们应该问这个问题
the salutogenic question: why do some individuals succeed
这个健康本源的问题 为什么有些人
despite unfavorable circumstances?
成长环境恶劣 依然能成功?
There were very good intentions before this question was asked.
即使不提出这个问题 他们也是心怀善意的
There was a lot of idealism.
充满理想主义
It wasn't enough.
这是不够的
Very often,some of these interventions engendered
很多时候 这些干预会产生
the passive victim mentality,
消极的受害者心态
as opposed to the active agent mentality
而不是积极作用者心态
that Marva Collins instilled,
这是Marva Collins提出的观点
the programs by Karen Reivich and Martin Seligman instill.
是根据Karen Reivich和Martin Seligman的研究所提的
And this is where psychology can help.
这正是心理学起作用的地方
Because we can take the research and apply it.
因为我们可以展开研究
We can take the research and apply it,
并应用到现实中
which goes back to the point why it is so important
又回到了那个问题 为什么
to bridge Ivory tower and Main Street.
搭起学校与社会的桥梁如此重要
Most of these research is not applied.
大多数这类研究并没运用于现实
So for example:
例如
how many teachers working in the classroom
有多少教师在课室努力工作
day in and day out know about the Pygmalion effect?
日复一日地研究皮格马利翁效应?
The Pygmalion effect that we are going to talk about
我们下周或再下周会探讨
next week or the week after,
皮格马利翁效应
shows how teachers' expectations are self-fulfilling prophecies.
说明为什么教师的期望就是自我实现的预言
And if we have high expectations,
如果我们有很高的期望
if we see the seed of greatness in the students,
如果我们在学生身上看到伟大的潜能
that seed of greatness is more likely to flourish.
那么这种潜能就更可能被激发
Or if we don't appreciate it,
或者 如果我们看不到这潜能
it will depreciate―wither and die.
它就会像刚萌芽的幼苗一样被扼杀
How many teachers know about these studies?
有多少教师了解这些研究?
And how they create through their beliefs
他们怎样通过自己的信念
the self-fulfilling prophecy when it comes to their students?
创造出自我实现的预言 来影响学生?
How many teachers know about Marva Collins?
有多少教师了解Marva Collins?
Every teacher in the world on the first day of teacher training
每个教师在第一次接受教师培训时
need to learn about Marva Collins and Pygmalion effect.
需要了解Marva Collins和皮格马利翁效应
They don't do that.
但事实并非如此
How about this?
接下来谈
Self-esteem.
自我尊重
How do you increase self-esteem?
你如何提升自尊?
If I have to do a poll here,most people,
如果我在这里做一项民意调查 保证大多数人
guaranteed,would say praise people.
会说通过赞美来提升
Praise people. Praise children.
赞美别人 赞美孩子
It will enhance their self-esteem.
这将增强他们的自尊
Right. Partially right.
说对了一部分
And if it's taken as the whole truth,
如果把这当作全部的真理
and nothing but the truth,it's detrimental.
则是有害的
Because there is a lot of research that shows
因为有很多研究显示
when we praise people indiscriminately,
当我们不加区别地赞扬别人
we are actually in the long run
我们实际上是在长期地
potentially hurting them more than helping them,
默默地伤害他们 而非帮助他们
whether it's their wellbeing,as well as their success.
无论是对他们的幸福感 还是成功
But the self-esteem movement mostly says
但关于提升自尊有个常见的说法
praise people,praise children all the time.
要经常赞美别人和孩子
And again,that's important.
这点很重要
But it's also important to know how to praise.
同样重要的是 要懂得如何赞美
How many people are familiar with the work
有多少人了解
of the Stanford psychologist,Carol Dweck.
斯坦福大学心理学家Carol Dweck的作品
Well,you are going to be familiar with it in a few weeks.
你们在这几周内会了解到
Many idealists with good intentions are not.
很多好心的理想主义者都不了解这些
And they continue to support or to practice
他们依然认为
self-esteem as indiscriminate praise,
提升自尊就要不加区别地赞扬
ultimately hurting more than helping.
这最终造成的伤害大于帮助
How many psychologists,or rather how many interventionists
有多少心理学家或干涉主义者
with good intentions are familiar
怀有好的意愿 同时又了解
with the work of Albert Bandura on self-efficacy?
Albert Bandura关于自我效能感论的研究?
And how you cultivate that?
要怎样培养?
Not enough.
还不够
And very often,more harm than good is created.
很多时候结果都是弊大于利
How many psychologists are familiar
有多少心理学家了解
with this new emerging field of the mind and the body?
这个心理和生理的新领域?
How many know about the studies that cheerful
有多少人知道下面这个让人欣慰的案例
example that yoga practice diminishes significantly,
瑜伽练习
more than any other interventions that they tried,
比任何试过的干预措施都有效
the likelihood of second-time offenders
犯人在监狱里练瑜伽
when they practice it in jail?
会降低他们的二次犯罪率
After their release,they are much less likely to return to jail
在狱中练过瑜伽的犯人
if they do some yoga there.
获释后较少会再进监狱
Strange,but true.
虽奇怪 但却是事实
How many people know that―
有多少人知道-
and this is connected to my first point―
这点与我提出的第一个观点有关-
that doing meditation actually literally transforms our brain,
多少人知道 冥想能转换我们的大脑思维
making us more susceptible to positive emotions
使我们更容易感染到积极情绪
and more resilient in the face of painful emotions.
在面对痛苦时更坚强
How many people know that three times a week
多少人知道 每周三次
physical exercise,30 minutes each time has the same effect
体育锻炼 每次三十分钟 与最强劲的精神药物
as our most powerful psychiatric drugs?
有同样的效果?
Three times a week for 30 minutes.
每周三次 每次30分钟
How many psychologists or psychiatrists prescribe
多少心理学家或精神科医生规定病人
"run three times a week and see me in the morning"?
"每周跑步锻炼三次 早上来见我"?
Not enough.
还不够
That's practical idealism coupled together.
这是实际与理想主义相结合
How are in conflict resolution,
在解决冲突时
the dominant theme of most people
大多数人
with good intentions want to resolve conflict
好心想要解决冲突
is let's get the people together,
让人们坐下来
let's get them to talk,
好好谈谈
and they and we will live happily ever after.
然后就能过上幸福快乐的日子
Well we have research from 1954―
我们有1954年的研究
those of you who take social psych―Muzafer sherif,
那些想从社会心理方面解决冲突的人 Muzafer Sherif
showing that the contact hypothesis
显示接触假说
which is just get people to talk to one another,
也就是让人们彼此交谈的方法
doesn't work;
并不起作用
in fact very often it worsens the situation―
很多时候反而让情况更糟
very often the conflict actually gets worse
很多时候会使冲突进一步恶化
as a result of just getting together and talking,
因为人们只是聚在一起进行商谈
that the contact is not enough,
接触还不够
that what you need,
你需要的是
in the words of Muzafer sherif
引用Muzafer警长的话
and later elaborated on by Elliot Aronson―
后来由Elliot Aronson详细阐述-
what you need is a superordinate goal―
你需要的是一个非常明确的目标
a goal that you have carry out together,
一个得集体实现的目标
that you cannot do by yourself―
你自己一人做不来的
carry out together with a conflicting group.
由一个内部有冲突的小组来实现
And that's how over time you resolve conflicts,
这样随着时间的推移 就能解决冲突
not just bring people together.
不仅是让人们聚在一起而已
Now as you can imagine,this is very close to home for me.
可以想到 这离我们的意愿不远了
Because there were many people on both sides
因为在阿拉伯 以色列冲突中
of the Arab/Israeli conflict who wanted to end it,
双方都有很多人想结束战争
many people in this country who wanted to end it.
美国也有很多人想结束它
So what did they do?
他们做了什么呢?
Let's just get them together. Let's get them in a room,
我们把他们关到一个房间里吧
whether it was in Camp David,whether it was in Oslo or in Egypt.
无论是在戴维营 奥斯陆或埃及
Let's just get them together to talk,to resolve their conflict
让他们交谈 解决他们的冲突
and their issue and then we will all live happily ever after.
和他们的问题 然后我们就能过上幸福生活
What happened?
那样会发生什么事呢?
The situation worsened.
局势会恶化
Now we've known that.
现在我们都知道这个道理了
Muzafer sherif showed that in 1954
Muzafer警长在1954年就证明了
that it is the most likelihood outcome
接触假设 只让人们一起交谈
of just contact hypothesis,just getting them to be together.
最可能的结果是引起更多冲突
And there were many people trying to resolve the conflict,
有很多人都试图解决冲突
not just in the Middle East,else in the world,
不只在中东 世界各地都有这种情况
with very good intentions
人们都心存好意
but very often making inadvertently the matters worse.
但往往在不经意间使事情变得更糟
Idealism and good intentions are not enough.
理想主义和善意是不够的
We need to merge,to mate the research with the practice.
我们需要将理论结合实践
And this is where you come in,
需要你们这样做
taking it seriously.
认真对待
Now when I take it seriously,
但当我认真对待这事
there is a problem here
就出现了一个问题
because sometimes research doesn't deliver good news.
有时研究所得并不一定是好消息
It would be much easier and nicer
如果仅仅是将
if we could just simply get
以色列人和阿拉伯人聚在一起 冲突就结束
Israelis and Arabs together and the conflict would end.
那事情就简单得多 容易得多
It would be much nicer and easier,smoother,
这将让事情变得更简单
it would be much easier,
非常容易
if we could just cultivate children self-esteem
如果我们要培养孩子自尊
by giving them positive feedback―
仅仅通过多一些赞美
telling them how wonderful they are.
告诉他们 他们有多棒
It's easy to do,right?
这很容易做到 不是吗?
It feels good. They feel good. We feel good.
这样感觉很好 他们感觉良好 我们也是
But in the long run,it doesn't help,if it's only that.
但从长远来看 仅仅这样做并没有帮助
Much easier.
只是容易而已
And research very often delivers bad news,
研究往往带来坏消息
saying it's not enough-- the contact;
只是接触还不够
it's not enough to praise.
只是赞扬还不够
And then people choose subconsciously,
然后人们下意识地选择
not consciously to ignore the research and go with her heart.
不自觉地忽视研究所得的坏结果
And that's important to go with your heart.
虽然跟随自己的感觉是重要
But it's important to with the heart and the mind.
但更重要的是同时注重感觉和思维
Imagine if an aeronautics engineer
试想一下 如果一个航空工程师
woke up in the morning and said,
在早上醒来 说:
"you know,the Law of Gravity thing
"万有引力
really makes things difficult for me.
真的带给我很多麻烦
It's a pain.
很麻烦
Things would be so much easier without the law of gravity.
如果没有万有引力 事情就易办多了
The design would be simpler."
航空设备也不用这么麻烦"
And he designs airplane and he ignores the law of gravity.
然后他决定不考虑万有引力设计飞机
What kind of airplane machine would he or she design?
他会设计出怎样一架飞机呢?
A failure.
肯定会失败
Aeronautics engineer takes into consideration of reality.
航空工程师必定要考虑到现实
And reality-- there's Law of Gravity.
现实就是万有引力的存在
We deal with that.
我们得接受现实
Similarly,what research shows us is reality:
同样 研究显示的结果就是现实
what's out there,what's working and what's not working.
有哪些现象 哪些可行 哪些不可行
And we need to conform to it.
我们需要遵循现实
Take it into consideration.
考虑现实
And it's up to you,to take responsibility,
能否搭起学校与社会的桥梁
to bridge the Ivory tower and Main Street.
取决于我们自己
You are being exposed in 32 classes fraught your Harvard career
在哈佛你们会有32种专业
to the most rigorous thinking on different topics
各自的课程有不同的主题
have you take it and apply it,
你要将这些知识一一吸收并应用
whether it's psychology,whether it's in economics,
无论是心理学还是经济学
obviously in engineering or computer science,
当然如果是工程学或计算机科学
where it's done much more readily
就会比社会科学和人文科学
than in social sciences and humanities.
更容易理解
It's important to take responsibilities,
重点是 你要为自己负责
because no one else is going to do it for you.
因为没人会来帮你
No one is coming.
没人会帮你
Premise 2:
第二前提
To be a practical idealist,
作为一个实际的理想主义者
the foundation of it has to be
它的基础必须是
the belief that change is possible.
相信改变是可能的
Because if the change was not possible on the individual level,
因为如果从个人层面或社会层面来说
on the society level,why am I doing what I am doing?
改变都是不可能的 那我在这里干什么?
Why would I spend time?
为什么我要花时间在这里?
Let me just be a hedonist,
倒不如做个享乐主义者
trying to enjoy my life as much as possible.
尽情享受生活
Now for many of you,when you look at this you may say,
你们可能会说
"Well,Ok,yes,change is possible.
"好吧 改变是有可能的
I believe that and why do we need to have it
我相信这一点 但为什么我们需要把它
as a basic premise of the course,
作为课程的基本前提
as opposed to change is illusive?"
而不说'改变是虚幻的'?"
Well,in the context of a psychology course,
在心理学上
it's anything but trivial that change is possible.
改变是有可能的 这点十分重要
Let me share with you one study to illustrate what I mean.
下面我用一项研究来说明
The Minnesota Twin study,
明尼苏达州的双胞胎研究
one of the most famous studies in the field of psychology,
一个在心理学领域非常有名的研究
was done by Lykken and Tellegen,two prominent psychologists.
是两个杰出的心理学家Lykken和Tellegen做的
And what they did was they wanted to understand
这个研究是关于
how much do genes matter.
基因的重要性
How much is it about nature versus nurture?
与教育相比 它对性格的影响多大?
So how do you test that?
要如何测试呢?
You look at identical twins,
同卵双胞胎
monozygotic twins who share the same genetic profile.
他们拥有相同的基因谱
And you look at those who are reared apart.
研究那些被分开抚养长大的同卵双胞胎
Because if they are reared by the same parents,one could argue,
因为如果他们由相同的父母抚养 人们会说
"Well they came out very similar because same environment:
"他们这么相似 是因为有同样的成长环境
they look the same; they go to the same schools;
他们外表一模一样 上一样的学校
same parents,and so on."
有同样的父母 等等"
But what if you are able to find identical twins
如果你能找到 出生时就分开了的
who were separated at birth,
同卵双胞胎
and reared in radically different environments.
在完全不同的环境里长大
Well you could.
现实中能找到这种人
And they found significant number of those,
学者发现有很多这样的人
reared in,sometimes different continents.
有时甚至在不同的洲长大
And they studied them.
他们对这些双胞胎进行了研究
And what they found remarkably
发现了一个明显的现象
was significant similarities among these twins,
这些双胞胎极其相似
sometimes to the points of unbelievable.
有时相似之处非常惊人
Like one set of twins―
像有一组双胞胎
I think they found the wives with the same name.
他们娶了名字相同的妻子
They were reared in different countries,
他们在不同的国家长大
didn't know about each other until the age of 37―
直到37岁才知道对方的存在
married similar wives,enjoyed drinking the same beer,
娶了相似的妻子 喝同一种啤酒
called their children by the same names.
为自己的孩子取相同的名字
There were some mind-boggling similarities.
有些相似之处令人难以置信
And this is an exception,
有例外
but there were quite a few of those exceptions.
但也只有很少例外
But more interesting for psychologists
让心理学家更感兴趣的是
was that their personality was incredibly similar.
他们的个性非常相似
And very interesting for positive psychologists,
让积极心理学学者 和研究幸福和快乐的人
those concerned with wellbeing and happiness:
更感兴趣的是
their wellbeing and happiness levels were incredibly similar.
这些双胞胎的幸福和快乐水平非常相似
Even if they were raised in radically different environments.
即使他们在完全不同的环境中长大
Lykken and Tellegen published a paper,
Lykken和Tellegen发表了一篇文章
a very influential paper in the 80s,
一篇在80年代非常有影响力的论文
which they called "Happiness is a Stochastic Phenomenon".
论文题为"幸福是一种随机现象"
And they end this paper with the following quote:
论文用以下这句话作结尾
"It may be that trying to be happier
"想变得更快乐
is as futile as trying to be taller
和想变高一样徒劳
and is therefore counterproductive."
只会适得其反"
This quote made me very unhappy on two accounts.
这句话有两方面让我觉得不快
This wa s a very influential quote.
这是句非常有影响力的名言
This appeared in New York Times.
曾被登上《纽约时报》
They talked about on television.
他们也在电视上说过这话
They were interviewed.
受访时也说过
Very problematic.
这就有问题了
Coz what are we doing here?
那我们在这里做什么?
If this is the outcome of the research,
如果这是那次研究的结果
a rigorous research that they did―
一项严谨的研究
not an easy research to go and look around the world,
而不是马马虎虎的轻松的研究
what can we do about it?
我们能做些什么呢?
Here is my response to that:
我认为
Very simply,change is possible.
简单来说 改变是可能的
And again,don't take my word for it of course.
别盲目相信我的话
Let me discuss that further-- elaborate.
下面我来详细阐述这话
There is account of evidence
有证据显示
where people actually do change
人们的确是会改变的
and we have research showing that people going to therapy
我们有研究显示 经常接受治疗的人
very often change as the a result of therapy.
会容易改变
Work by Albert Bandura,Stanford psychologist
斯坦福大学的心理学家Albert Bandura的研究
shows that very often people encountering one special sentence,
表明 人们常因遇到一个特别的句子
reading it or hearing it from something,
读到或听到它
that sentence can change their lives,
这句话就会改变他们的生活
reading it on certain book,having certain experiences―
在书上读到 或是有某种经历-
positive or painful experiences C
积极的或痛苦的经历-
there is this concept of Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder (PTSD).
有这样一个概念叫做 创伤后应激障碍(PTSD)
There is also a concept of Post-Traumatic Growth.
还有一种概念叫做 创伤后成长
So people change-- up or down in their level of happiness
人们的快乐水平会上下变化
is a result of their experiences.
这是他们的经验之谈
So there is counter evidentce that shows that not everyone,
有可靠证据显示 并非每一个人的
level of wellbeing is determined by their genes.
幸福水平都取决于基因
In fact,there is research
事实上 有研究
that shows yes genes do matter and they matter a lot,
显示基因很重要 影响甚多
as we'll talk about during the week on change.
探讨改变的时候我们再谈这问题
Other things matter as well.
还有其他因素和基因一样重要
And the error that Lykken and Tellegen and many others make
像Lykken和Tellegen那样 人们常错误地
when they generalize and say "change is not possible"
概括出一个结论 "变化是不可能的"
is what I call "the error of the average".
我称之为"大众错误"
Yes,on average,
平均而言
when you look at this group of 40 or 50 twins reared apart,
当研究这40或50组被分开抚养的双胞胎
when you look at the average,
大体看来
they are just about the same.
他们是一样的
However,that's not looking at the individuals
然而 没有单独来看
because while many of them are the same,
因为 虽然他们大多数是非常相似的
not all are the same.
但并不是全部都一样
It reminds me of a joke about the statistician
这让我想起一个统计学笑话
who drowned in a pool with an average height of 10 inches.
在一个平均水深为10英寸的游泳池里 谁会被淹死
You see you cannot tell the height or the depth rather
只知道平均值
of a pool based on the average.
并不知道游泳池的水深
Because that pool may be average of 10 inches,
由于该池平均10英寸深
but maybe it has places that are 20 feet deep,
或许它某些区域有20英尺深
if it's a large pool.
如果它是一个大水池的话
The same when you look at the average of individuals and twins.
同样 当你平均地看这些双胞胎
The majority on average,they are extremely similar.
大体来说 他们都极其相似
But there are also outliers.
但也有少数的异常值
And very often,it's the outliers,
很多时候 这个异常值
the differences that are the most interesting.
这些差异最有趣
Because they stretch―
因为他们
not just our imagination-- they stretch our ability to understand
不只延伸了我们的想象 还让我们能理解
when and where change is possible.
怎样的时间和地点 有可能产生变化
The question when we see exceptions,
当我们看到了例外-
whether it's the Lykken and Tellegen study,
无论是在Lykken和Tellegen的研究
where we do see exceptions―
还是别的出现了例外的研究-
not all twins were the same,
当发现不是所有的双胞胎都一样
majority were,but not all―
主要的问题
the question is no longer whether or not change is possible,
已不再是 改变是否有可能
but rather how is change possible.
而是怎样实现这种改变
Once again,the exception proves the rule.
例外证实了那个规律
And the research that argues
认为"改变是不可能"的
that it's not possible to change,is detrimental.
研究是有害的
Think about an eight year old girl,
设想一个8岁的女孩
who's very unhappy,
她很忧伤
and then reads some magazine about that study,
然后在杂志上读到那个研究
saying that basically you are genetically set point
研究告诉她 基本上你的基因决定了一切
what you are born with is there for life.
你与生俱来的一切 将伴随你终生
She's unhappy.
她会更忧伤
She feels anxious and miserable as an 8 year old.
她只有8岁 但会觉得非常焦虑与痛苦
And she says to herself,
她就会想
"That's it. That's my lot in life. I was born unlucky."
"我的人生就是这样 我生来不幸"
And that,very often,becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy.
那很可能会成为一个自我实现的预言
And she remains unhappy.
她始终不快乐
Sometimes it even makes her less happy than she was before.
有时这研究让她比以前更不快乐
Because now she's also helpless.
因为现在她简直是绝望了
Change is possible.
改变是可能的
You know I often say that
你知道我经常说
I am the right the person to teach positive psychology.
我是教积极心理学的最佳人选
Why?
为什么?
Because I wasn't born with "happy genes".
因为我不是生来就有"快乐基因"
I was born with,genetically speaking,
从遗传学上讲 我天生就
relatively high level of anxiety,
比较容易焦虑
inclination toward rumination,
容易得抑郁症
over-examination―
这是经过测试证实的
we'll talk about that later in the course.
在后面的课程上我们会谈到
I went into the positive psychology,
我之所以研究积极心理学
into the field of psychology,
探索心理学领域
as I mentioned in the first lecture,
正如我第一节课时提到的
because I was unhappy here.
是因为我不快乐
And over time,as a result of many of these studies,
随着时间的推移 出现了很多这类研究
result of examination result of asking also the right questions,
由于提出了正确的问题
I have become happier.
我变得更快乐
So on a personal level,I know it's possible to become happier.
个人层面上 是有可能变得更快乐
Now I am happier today than I was fifteen years ago
现在的我比15年前的我更快乐
when I started. I hope to be happier 15 years
我希望15年后的我
from today than I am today.
比今天的我更快乐
It's a life-long process.
这是个终身的过程
But it is possible. And many people show that it's possible.
但这是有可能的 很多人证实了这是有可能的
And those who argue it's not possible
而那些认为这不可能的人
and use science to argue for that,
他们用科学来争论
very often,are hurting more than helping the field.
很多时候 只有阻碍作用而毫无帮助
Now by the way Lykken and Tellegen were interviewed
最近Lykken和Tellegen
recently in TIME magazine issue of happiness.
受到《时代》杂志的采访 谈"快乐"问题
Let me quote to you what they said.
下面是他们说的几句话
This is in 2005-- Lykken:
2005年 Lykken说
"I made a dumb statement.
"我作了一个愚蠢的声明
It is clear that we can change happiness levels,up or down."
显然 我们能改变快乐水平 变得更高或更低"
So they went back on their statement.
于是他们背弃了原来的声明
It was a sensational statement at the time.
这个声明轰动一时
It certainly is possible.
改变当然是可能的
So how do we do research that's more responsible,
我们怎样做更负责任的研究
that does not lead to detrimental results?
怎样杜绝研究产生坏影响?
And at the same time,true.
同时 研究必须是真实的
We don't want to invent research.
我们并不是要"发明"研究
Research is about identifying things
研究的目的在于查明事实
that really occur/happen in reality.
现实中真正发生了的事实
So one of the first things that I'll argue for in terms of
首先 我认为在健康研究方面
healthy research is "let's also focus on what is working".
主要的问题是"让我们注重可行的方法"
That's first thing that we discussed in the past lecture.
这是我们过去探讨过的问题
The second thing that I will argue for
第二 我认为
in addition to studying what works is also to study the best.
除了要研究可行的方法 还要研究最优秀的个体
What do I mean by best?
为什么说"最优秀的个体"呢?
Let's not just study what makes people happy.
我们不但要研究人们因何快乐
Let's not just study happy people.
不要只是研究快乐的人
Let's not just study happy relationships and good relationships.
不要只是研究快乐良好的爱情
Let's study the happiest people.
让我们研究的最快乐的人
Let's study the most successful relationships
让我们研究最成功的爱情
and learn from that.
从中学习借鉴
That is a radically different approach
这是个与大众研究
than studying just the average.
完全不同的研究方法
Because what I am saying here is "let's not study the average",
我想说的是 不要研究大众
let's study the top five percent
研究快乐指数最高的5%的人
so that we can understand the phenomenon better.
这样就可以更好地理解这一现象
The person who talks about this is Abraham Maslow.
这就是Abraham Maslow
When he talked about "growing-tip" statistics.
提出的"成长尖端统计学"
Let me read to you-- this is taken from his book:
以下这话引自他的书
"What this kind of research design means
"设计出这类调研是为了
is a change in our conception of statistics,
改变我们对统计的观念
and especially of sampling theory.
尤其是对抽样调查的看法
What I am frankly espousing here
我非常支持
is what I have been calling "growing-tip statistics,"
'成长尖端统计学'
taking my title from the fact
我的头衔来自以下的研究发现
that it is at the growing tip of a plant
最优秀的遗传基因会在
that the greatest genetic action takes place."
幼苗的成长尖端出现"
What he's saying is that
他的意思是
"let's study the sages,the saints,
"让我们学习圣人
the extraordinary people,the arrowhead"
非凡的人"
so that we can understand and realize
这样能帮助我们了解
the potential in all people.
人类的潜能
Let me quote him in greater length.
我再引述他另一句更长的话
This is very important,which is why I am doing it:
这话非常重要 是我作这个研究的原因
"If we want to know how fast a human being can run,
"如果想知道人类最快能跑多快
then it is no use to average out the speed of a "good sample"
那从好的样本中测出平均数是
of the population;
没用的
it is far better to collect Olympic gold medal winners
而应该收集田径类奥运冠军的信息
and see how well they can do.
看他们能跑多快
If we want to know the possibilities for spiritual growth,
如果想知道心灵成长的可能性
value growth or moral development in human being,
人类价值增长或道德发展的可能性
then I maintain that we can learn most
那我认为 我们可以研究
by studying our most moral,ethical,or saintly people.
最道德或圣洁的人
On the whole I think it fair to say that human history
整体来说 我认为人类历史
is a record of the ways in which human nuture
是人性逐渐缺失的过程的
has been sold short.
一个记录
The highest possibilities of human nature
人性的潜在极限
have practically always been underrated.
实际上一直被低估了
Certainly it seems more and more clear that what we call "normal"
显然 我们平常称之为'正常'的东西
in psychology is really a psychopathology of the average,
在心理学上 实际是种大众精神病理
so undramatic and so widely spread
看上去平平无奇却又非常广泛
that we don't even notice it ordinarily."
我们甚至没有注意到它"
You see,
你们明白
the implications of what he's saying here?
他话里的含义吗?
Essentially what he's saying is
基本上 他的意思是
"let's not just study why do most individuals fail;
"不要只研究为什么大多数人失败
let's also study why do some-- not many―
让我们也研究为什么有些人
but why do some individuals succeed despite the circumstances".
但为什么有的人尽管条件恶劣也能成功"
Let's not study just the average
不要只研究整体
that says that people can't really change.
整体看来的话 人是不能改变的
Let's study those people who have changed,
让我们来研究改变了的人
who have literally transformed their lives
真的改变了自身生活
and those lives around them.
和身边其他人生活的人
This is a radical approach to research.
这是个激进的研究方法
This is a radical approach to the search,
对研究我们自身来说
to studying ourselves as well.
这也是个激进的方法
Because very often,if we only study the average,
因为很多时候 如果我们只研究平均水平
we only see the average,we only see the geometric shapes
那就只会看到平均的结果 只看到几何形状
and completely missed the children on the bus.
完全忽略了汽车上的孩子
And very often,
很多时候
the answer to some of our most pressing questions
最紧迫的问题的答案
lies in the extraordinary―
出人意料
lies on the children on the bus.
就在汽车的孩子身上
Now does anyone other than me―
除了我还有其他人
because I admit that I fall into this category―
我承认我属于这一类
but anyone other than me feel a little bit disease
但有谁在听到我说的这些话时
when I talk about this?
感到不舒服吗?
Seriously,a little bit disease when I talk about
说真的 当我谈到
"let's focus on studying the best―
"让我们集中精力研究最优秀的个体 圣人 非凡的人"
the saint,the sages,the extraordinary"?
有人感到不舒服吗?
I feel disease.
我觉得不大舒服
I'm sure some of you feel that too.
你们有些人应该也有这感觉
Because after all,isn't that elitist?
因为这难道不是精英主义吗?
Shouldn't we study the average
我们不是应该研究普罗大众吗?
because we concern not just with elites?
因为我们关心的不只是精英
We are concerned with the average.
我们关心的是普罗大众
So there are two answers to that―
以下的问题有两个原因
why I still maintain,and I must admit
我为什么还要继续说?我必须承认
I still feel some disease every time I teach this,
每次教到或想到这个统计
every time I think about this and I think too,
我就觉得有点不舒服
why it is so important to study the best,
研究最优秀的个体 为什么如此重要
why the "growing-tip" statistics is
为什么成长尖端统计学
such an important approach to research that I encourage
如此重要 我要建议
my students to carry out.
大家使用
First of all,
首先
because it is not to the exclusion of the average.
因为它不是排除了普罗大众
Just like positive psychology does not say "let's exclude
就像积极心理学不是说 排除不可行的事
what's not working; let's exclude study of pathology".
排除病理研究"
Similarly,"growing-tip" statistics is not saying
同样 成长尖端统计学不是提倡
"let's not study the average".
"我们别研究大众了"
It says "let's also study the best".
它提倡也去研究最优秀的个体
So this is the first thing to alleviate the concern of elitism.
因此在这问题上无须计较研究对象是不是精英
The second issue,the second response is even more important.
第二点 更为重要的是
Because everyone benefits,when we study the best.
研究最优秀的个体 能让每个人从中受益
And the "average"-- whatever that means,
而所谓的"大众"
the "average" benefits even more
在这种研究中
than the best of this kind of studies.
"大众"比"精英"受益更多
Why?
为什么呢?
For example: the study of resilience.
例如 对适应力的研究
We could have gone on and studied the average at-risk population
我们本可以继续研究几百年来的
for decades and centuries.
平均受危人群
And very little advances would have been made.
应该会取得一点点进展
Very little advances were made.
事实证明进展甚微
It was only when we started to study
只有当我们开始研究
those "best" examples,those successful kids,
这些"最优秀"的个体 成功的孩子
those "super" kids as they were initially named.
那些"超级"孩子
It was only when we started to study those
只有当我们开始研究这些
that we actually understood how we can best help that population.
才能了解如何帮助到整体
And once we applied our studies-- the resilience issue,
只要将心理韧性研究应用到生活中
everyone benefited and continued to benefit from it.
每个人受益良多
That's an example of "growing-tip" statistics research.
这就是个成长尖端统计学的研究实例
Or how about the study of meditation?
那关于冥想的研究呢?
So I want to study how to meditate.
我想研究冥想
Do I go out to Harvard yard and take a random sample
是不是可以在哈佛大二学生里随机抽样
of sophomores to study meditation?
来研究冥想?
Or do I go to a mountain top in Tibet
还是去西藏的山顶
and study the people who have been doing it for decades?
研究冥想了几十年的人?
Of course I go and study them!
当然我该去研究他们
This is exactly what psychologists did!
的确有心理学家这样做过
And they studied their brain―
他们研究了冥想者的大脑
we'll talk about it when we talk about meditation―
谈到冥想时再谈这问题
and they illustrated how their brain
通过研究说明他们的大脑
is transformed through meditation.
如何通过冥想来转换
Psychologists,like Jon Kabat Zinn,
像心理学家on Kabat Zinn
Richard Davidson and Herbert Benson,
Richard Davidson和Herbert Benson
were able to take what they learned from these extraordinary,
能从这些最优秀的个体中吸取经验
best individuals and apply it to other people's lives
并应用到普通人的生活中
so that now I benefit from meditation
如果我每天冥想15或20分钟
when I do it for 15 minutes or 20 minutes a day.
就能从中受益
And millions of other people,"the average",
千千万万的"普罗大众"
benefit a great deal because of the study of the best,
因对最优秀的个体的研究
of the "growing-tip".
而受惠
How about relationships?
那爱情呢?
Can you imagine
你能想象
a study of relationships throughout human history
对整个人类历史上的恋爱关系进行研究
that focuses on the average?
并求平均值吗?
What's the average relationship in human history?
人类史上的普通恋爱关系是指什么?
The average relationship in human history
人类史上的普通恋爱关系
is one in which the woman is subjugated.
其一是女人是被压制的一方
That's the average relationship in human history.
这就是人类史上的普通恋爱关系
Now what if we just study that?
如果我们只研究这种恋爱关系呢?
Would that be helpful?
是否有帮助?
No,it was when people like John Stuart Mill,
不 John Stuart Mill这样的人
who studied his relationships
研究了他自身的恋爱关系
which was at the time extraordinary,
这在当时是极不寻常的
realized the potential of what all relationships can be
研究过后他发现恋爱关系能改变
that he wrote his book on subjugation of women,
他这本书是以女性主导地位为题的
one of the most important books
这本书是19世纪最重要的书之一
of the 19th century that has led to the feminist movement
是女权运动和平等运动的
and to the equality movement.
导火线
What if he only studies the average?
如果他只研究普通的恋爱关系呢?
Would that help relationships?
那样对人际关系有帮助吗?
Not at all.
完全没有
How about teaching?
那教学呢?
What do you want to do in order to learn about teaching―
要了解如何教学 你想怎样做?
go and study the average teachers or go and study Marva Collins
研究平均水平的教师还是研究Marva Collins
and then apply what Marva Collins does to all teachers?
然后将Marva Collins的经验应用到所有老师身上?
Everyone benefits when we focus on the tip of stamen―
当着眼于研究最优秀的人体时 每个人都得益
this is why Maslow said human nature
这就是为什么Maslow说人性
and human potential has been sold short,
和人的潜能会被削弱
when we only study the average.
如果我们只研究平均水平的话
It's also about studying our personal best,
同样涉及到研究我们个人的最大长处
not just other people's best,
而不仅是研究其他人的最大长处
whether it's our personal best experiences because
无论是不是我们的最佳经验
if we study our best experiences when we are at our happiest,
因为研究我们的最开心
when we are at our most successful,
最成功
when we thrive the most within the relationship,
恋爱关系最佳时的状态
we can learn from it and apply it to our future as well.
那我们也可以从中学习并应用到将来
When we study our average,we are describing our lives.
当我们研究平均水平 我们只是描述日常生活
When we are studying the best within ourselves,
研究我们当中最优秀的个体时
we are potentially prescribing.
我们潜意识里在学习
Maslow again: "Few in number though they be,
Maslow又说:"虽然他们人数少
we can learn a great deal about values
但我们可以学到很多有用的东西
from the direct study of these highly evolved,
从对这些最优秀
most mature,psychologically healthiest individuals,
最成熟的 心理最健康的个体的研究当中
and from the study of the peak moments of average individuals,
和对大众的峰值的研究当中可以知道
moments,in which they become transiently self-actualized."
他们达到了短暂的自我实现"
If we learn from these experiences in ourselves,
如果我们自己吸取这些经验
the question is no longer whether or not it's possible
那么问题就不再是 是否有可能
to experience it more and more in our lives.
越来越多地体验它
The question is "how is it possible to experience it".
而是"怎样去体验它"
Alright.
好
So we talked about changing ourselves,
我们讨论过改变自己
how it's possible the "growing-tip" statistics
为什么成长尖端统计学
which is the second significant idea
会是积极心理学研究中的
within research in positive psychology:
第二个重要理念
first significant idea is "let's study what works"
第一个重要理念是"研究可行的事"
the second significant idea is "let's study what works best".
第二个重要理念是"研究最优秀的个体"
But this is about individual change.
但这是关乎个体的改变
How about societal change?
那社会变革呢?
I want to share with you at the end today a study,
最后我想介绍以下这项研究
one of the most famous studies in the field
心理学最有名的研究
called "the Cambridge-Somerville Youth Study psychology".
"剑桥-萨默维尔青年学习心理学"
This was the study that was run,
这项研究从上世纪30年代开始
starting in the 1930s right here between Harvard and MIT,
由哈佛大学与麻省理工学院共同进行
were the best minds―
这些人拥有最高的思维
psychological minds,philosophical minds,psychiatrists―
心理学思维 哲学思维 心理医生
got together and said,
他们聚在一起讨论
"let's create the Rolls-Royce―there wasn't a Rolls-Royce then―
"让我们做一个劳斯莱斯计划吧"
but best intervention program that we can think of."
"这是能想到的最佳干预方案"
There was no limit in terms of how much money was put into it.
他们没有金钱方面的限制
As much as they needed,
他们的一切要求都得到了满足
they got and they chose 250 kids from an at-risk population.
他们从受危人群中选了250名孩子
And the intervention is not a quick fix,
干预不是快速修复
overnight change,"we can" seminar-- five-year intervention.
不是能一夜改变的  他们实行五年干预
And here is what they got.
他们所做的是
Twice a month,case workers visited them,
工作人员每月两次探访受试者
helped them deal with the conflicts in the family,
帮助他们处理家庭中的冲突
helped them deal with issues in their lives.
以及处理日常生活中的问题
Half of them had academic tutoring,those who needed it―
他们中有一半人得到了学院的辅导
got help,academic help.
只要有需要 就能得到学术帮助
Psychiatric attention―
精神科医生也是
all those who needed it,they were there.
谁有需要 医生都随时候命
No limits on how much you needed it.
你可尽情利用这些资源
Whatever you needed,you got from the best minds in the field.
无论你需要什么 这些精英都能满足你
They joined the boy scouts,YMCA,
他们加入了童子军 基督教青年会
other youth movements,benefited a great deal,
或其他的青年运动 获益良多
supposedly from these experiences.
从这些经验可看出来
They got everything.
他们得到了一切
This would be a dream treatment―
这简直是梦寐以求的治疗
not just in the 1930s,today as well.
不仅在20世纪30年代 即使在今天也是
This is what psychologists dream about at night.
心理学家做梦也会梦到这些
Just introduce this.
这项研究就是这样进行的
And then measuring outcomes was as serious as the program itself.
调查结果非常重要
There was a random assignment―
还有一个随机分派项目
there were 250 kids who got nothing,
有另外250个孩子 他们什么也没得到
who were also studied,
也列为了研究对象
just like the kids who got the five-year intervention were studied―
就像受到"五年干预"的孩子一样
250 kids in the control group.
250名对照组的孩子
40 years follow-up.
40年的追踪调查
This was not just about today,tomorrow for the five years;
这调查不只是今天 明天或五年内的事
they followed them through much of their lives.
而是研究了他们的大半生
This was serious study.
这是一项非常严谨的研究
This was serious intervention.
这是严谨的干预
And the results were shocking.
其结果令人震惊
Even though all those who participated in this study―
即使所有参与这项研究的人-
whether it was the mental health workers,
无论是心理健康学者
whether it was the philosophers,psychologists,
哲学家 心理学家
the professors and the psychiatrists―
教授还是精神科医生-
praise the program as the best,as highly effective,
都说这是最佳 最高效的研究方案
when they looked at the raw objective data,
但当他们看到原始的样本数据
the results were shocking.
调研结果让他们震惊
Juvenile offenses:
少年犯罪
control group versus intervention group-- no difference.
对照组与干预组没有区别
Over a third had official records
超过三分之一有案底
and 20 more percent had unofficial records for misdemeanors.
超过20%犯轻罪 无案底
No difference in juvenile offenses.
在少年犯罪方面两组并无差异
Adult offenses later on in their lives.
成人后的犯罪率
Again,no difference.
同样没有区别
Over 20 percent offenses―
20%以上的犯罪率
whether against property or against person―
无论是对财产或对人所犯的罪
in both groups: the 250 here versus 250 here,
在这两组之间
which is significant sample size.
样本规模相同的两组间
No difference whatsoever.
并无差异
other measures:
其他测量数据显示
physical health and mental health―no difference whatsoever.
身体健康和心理健康 两组没有区别
But finally,there was a significant difference on alcoholism,
酗酒方面两组有显著差异
the number of people who became
酗酒人数有差异
alcoholic later on in life as well as job status―
工作地位有差异
how many people were able to
成为白领的人数
getting to do "the white collar" jobs.
两组有差异
So at least there are results there.
所以至少还是有成果的
At least they found statistically significant results
至少发现了几点显著的结果
when they came to that.
当发现这几个差异时
That's good,right?
那很棒吧
Not at all.
其实不尽然
Because these results were "in the wrong direction",
这些研究结果被扭曲了
meaning there were alcoholics in the intervention group
这项研究实际表明 干预组酒鬼数量
than in the control group;
比对照组更多
there were more people in the control group
对照组更多人
making it at work "raising their status at work"
在工作上表现出色
than in the intervention group.
相较干预组而言
In other words,intervention did more harm than good.
换而言之 干预弊大于利
Idealism,good intention,a lot of money wasn't practical.
理想主义 良好意愿 钱财 都是不切实际的
Now many people who look at this study―
很多关注这项研究的人
this is a seminal study―very few studies
这是一个开创性的研究 心理学史上
in the history of psychology that were that serious.
很少如此重要的研究
They say,"well,societal change is probably not possible".
他们认为"社会变革应该是不可能的"
Give me one minute and I'll finish.
再给我一分钟 快讲完了
Societal change is not possible,they say.
他们认为 社会变革是不可能的
Is it?
是吗?
First of all,there are exceptions and we have exceptions
首先 例外是存在的 我们中也有例外
that prove the rule--there are programs that actually work,
这证实了规则-有一个真正可行的方案
whether it's the work again of Karen Reivich
无论是Karen Reivich的研究
and Martin Seligman from U Penn,"resilience program",
还是宾夕法尼亚大学Martin Seligman的"适应力计划"
whether it's Marva Collins who's certainly an exception,
Marva Collins肯定是个例外
who shows how interventions work.
她显示了干预是如何起作用的
And it's interesting to think about
想想以下这个有趣的问题
the difference of what Marva Collins does,
Marva所做的事与那项研究的区别
or she doesn't give the students in sense of entitlement,
她没有给学生权利意识
or she praises them but she gives them hard love
她赞扬他们 给他们严厉的爱
as opposed to free lunch,
而不是免费的午餐
or she doesn't label them as needy
她没有按需要来将他们分类
and the study perhaps labeled these kids as needy.
那项研究大概是根据需要来划分孩子的
There are many differences.
有许多差异
But the keys to study this exception
但研究这个例外的关键是
and for practical idea is to come together
大家坐在一切
and to say "what is working? Let's study the best;
说"什么是可行的?我们研究最好的吧
let's study what works and then apply it."
研究可行的事 将它应用到生活中"
Let's spread the word.
我们将这思想传播出去
Let's do what Maslow talked about back in 1950s.
我们根据Maslow20世纪50年代所说的来行事
What he suggested is "Manhattan-Project-type attacks
他表明"曼哈顿计划"反驳了
upon what I consider to be the truly Big Problems of our time,
当时最大的问题
not only for psychology but for all human beings
这不仅是对心理学 甚至对所有人类都
with any sense of historical urgency".
带来了历史紧迫感"
The Manhattan Project,when they created the atomic bomb
曼哈顿计划中 他们创造了原子弹
and whether or not you agree with
无论你是否同意
the Manhattan Project normatively.
这计划
One second. I'm almost done.
很快就说完
Positively,what they did there was bring together the best minds
积极地说 他们汇集了最优秀的人才
Oppenheimer,Zillart,Fermi Feinman,Bore―
奥本海默 基拉特 费米费曼 波尔
bring them together with a mission of saving the free world.
联合他们 共同拯救自由世界
Again whether you agree or not with the project
无论你是否同意这计划
is beside the point,it was the greatest,positively speaking,
积极来说 它都是最伟大的计划
scientific project in history where the minds got together.
聚集起了最优秀的人才
This is what Maslow is suggesting that psychologists do.
这就是Maslow建议心理学家该做的事
This is also the aim of positive psychology,no less than this.
同时也是积极心理学的目标
You get people around the world to think about these problems,
让全世界的人们思考这些问题
these issues-- practical idealists
实际的理想主义者
who will study what works,
研究可行的方法
who will study the best and through that,make a difference.
研究最好的个体 他们会带来改变
I'll see you next week.
下周再见